Izzy Young collection, 1942-2015
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series II: Sound recordings, ca. 1960-1975
  - Stagnant Eagle and the Strangebirds, 1965, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR029)
    Performers include Paul Levine, Lee Kotick, Bob Fire, Nancy Lane, Danny Kagen, and Danny Kohn. Song list and performer credits listed on tape box.
  - Paul Siegel, #4, #5, #6, Tape 1, 1968, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR031)
  - Unidentified content, 1969, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR032)
  - Izzy Young folk show, 1969-07-12, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR033)
    Includes performances by Danny Hamburg Group, Howling Wolf, and Jimmie Joe.
  - Memphis crowd, 1969-09-06, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR034)
    "Memphis crowd sorrel. Izzy can be heard recorded for radio show. Part 2 of 4."
  - Izzy Young folk show, 1969-07-12, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR035)
    "Izzy Young folk show. Blues show, nothing live, TLL Records." From reel: "Church RMT Marathon."
  - Obray Ramsey and Byard Ray, 1970-06-25, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR036)
    Obray Ramsey and Byard Ray at the home of Israel Young.
  - Israel Goodman Young reading, 06-16-1970, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR037)
  - Joel Oppenheimer, ca. 1965, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR038)
  - Tuli Kupferberg from Listen to the Mockingbird, 1965, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR039)
  - Tom Paley, Folklore Center, 1969-02-12, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR040)
    Part 3 of 3.
  - Donny Cassidy, 1966-06-17, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR041)
    Katy lectures, up to Coda.
  - Darco String Band festival, 1960, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR042)
    Tape 1 (Kenny, Andy, John). Iron Mountain String Band.
  - Young Tradition program, 1968-11-18, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR043)
    Tracks include "Chicken on a raft," "The barley straw," "The long Peggin' Awl," "Knight William" and "The shepherd's daughter," "Banks of Clandy," "Brisk young widow," "The bawks of the vile," "A dieu maer" (American hymn from Sacred Harp), "Oh dear oh."
  - Ted Joans, 1968-09-29, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR044)
    Copy, tape #1.
  - Paul Areson, 1960, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR045)
  - 1961 Folk Festival, 1961, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR046)
    #10. WRVR.
  - Poetry reading for Open City, 1968-11-29, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR047)
    Tape II.
  - A.L. Lloyd, 1960, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR048)
  - WBAI folk show, 1969-08-23, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR049)
    Instrumental/religious song (Joe, Mark Jakobson), "Donovan's Josie," Janine Pommy Vega poetry, Bob Melanky?. Part 3 of 4.
  - Mike Seeger, 1966-12-12, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR050)
    Cafe Sahbra. #1 violinist, background music. Note from Mike Seeger in Accompanying documentation for sound recordings: "I agree to allow WKCR-radio to broadcast the concert recorded at the Folklore Center on Dec. 12, 1966. WKCR will edit this tape as to content or for technical reasons." Note from AFC engineer: "There is a very strong 120Hz hum that runs throughout the tape."
  - Joel Oppenheimer, 1963-05-25, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR051)
    Set II.
  - David Bromberg, 1960, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR052)
    Reel 4 of 4.
  - Jean Ritchie, 1969-01-06, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR053)
    Tape II. Song 1, "Pretty Betty...," "The lady gay," "12 days of...," "Brightest and best," "Amazing grace."
  - Young Tradition program, 1968-11-18, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR054)
    Reel 2 of 2. "Watercress-o," "The innocent hare" (wow and flutter, no good), "Lyke wake dirge," "The prentice boy," "Wondrous love," "Byker hill," "Daddy fox" (mono both channels).
  - Iron Mountain Stringband, 1960, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR055)
    Eric Davidson, banjo; Caleb Finch, fiddle; Peggy Haine, guitar. Tracks include "Train on the island," "Poor Ellen Smith," "Old Jimmy Sutton," "Little Maggie," "Lord Thomas and fair Ellender," "Mississippi sawyers," "Sourwood mountain."
  - Winnie Winston and Dave Bromberg, 1960, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR056)
  - Hilda Sims, 1964-02-18, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR057)
    British songs.
  - Tom Paley, 1960, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR058)
  - 1971 Festival of American Folklife, 1971-07, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR059)
    July 1-5, Bakers Union.
  - Elizabeth Cotten concert, 1965, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 10 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR060)
  - Unidentified recording, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 10 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR061)
  - Unidentified recording, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 10 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR062)
  - Unidentified recording, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 10 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR063)
  - Unidentified recording, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 10 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR064)
  - Folk I, Theo Bikel and Izzy Young, Radio Ad, October 17, 1970, undated, 1962, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR065)
    Folk I, 10/17/1970; Theo Bikel, Izzy Young; Radio Ad, 1962: Ron Cliff, Swedish Walter Armsby, Goat Horn Cow Horn, Marc Silber.
  - Jerry Rodolitz at the Folklore Center, March 29, 1967, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR066)
    1. New poem, just written. 2. Discussion of last lines of poems.
  - Izzy Young Folk Show: Danny Hamburg, July 12, 1969, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR067)
  - Unidentified recording, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR068)
  - Pal Olle, radio, 1963, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR069)
    Description in Swedish.
  - Debbie Heilner, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR070)
    Words and music by Debbie Heilner, Aaron Kramer, and Irwin Heilner. See tape box image for song list.
  - Rizzo: Italian language reading, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR071)
  - Raimon, WSUMC, May 25, 1970, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR072)
  - Stephen Grossman (II), undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR073)
  - Folklore Center: Aaron Kramer #1, 1967-1968, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR074)
    Two dates written on tape box: November 27, 1967 and April 7, 1968.
  - Folklore Center: Aaron Kramer #2, April 7, 1968, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR075)
  - Folklore Center: Aaron Kramer NYU, tape #1, April 25, 1968, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR079)
  - Folklore Center: Aaron Kramer NYU, tape #2, April 25, 1968, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR076)
  - Save the Children (concert), undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR077)
  - Hedy West at the Folklore Center, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR078)
  - Unidentified recording, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR080)
  - Unidentified recording, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR081)
  - Unidentified recording, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 7 in. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR082)
  - Pete Seeger, August 24, 1990, 1 sound cassette: analog. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR083)
  - Pete Seeger: Press Conference. Near Tonder, Denmark, August 25, 1990, 1 sound cassette: analog. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR084)
  - WBAI New York: Pete Seeger, Sis Cunningham, Gil Turner, Izzy Young, Bob Dylan, May 1962, 1 sound cassette: analog. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR085)
  - WBAI Broadside show: Izzy Young, Pete Seeger, Gil Turner, Sis Cunningham, Bob Dylan, May 1962, 1 sound cassette: analog. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR086)
  - Izzy Young, November 1991, 1 sound cassette: analog. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR087)
  - Izzy in Pittsburgh, undated, 1 sound cassette: analog. (Item-id AFC 2015/040: SR088)
- Series III: Graphic Images, ca. 1950-2015
  Includes photographic prints, negatives, and contact sheets of Izzy Young and the Folklore Center and Folklore Centrum, as well as photographs of and with prominent folk musicians. Includes photographs taken by David Gahr.
  - Subseries A: Black-and-white photographs
    - Folk scene photographs, ca. 1950-1984 (Box-folder 118/1-3)
      Includes photographic prints by David Gahr of Izzy Young and the Folklore Center, Izzy Young with prominent folk musicians, and other documentation of the NYC folk music scene. Includes a photograph of Izzy's father(?) working at his bagel bakery, circa 1950, and a photo of Young with daughter, Philomene Grandin. Includes photos of Pete Seeger, Pentangle, the Fugs, Dave Van Ronk, Allen Ginsberg and Peter Orlovsky, Richie Havens, Mike Seeger, and Judy Collins.
    - Music photographs, Sweden, ca. 1972-1995 (Box-folder 118/4-5)
      Includes photographic prints of Izzy Young, (Swedish?) musicians, and Pete and Mike Seeger. Several of the photos include content on the backs about photographer or subject.
    - Folklore Centrum and family photographs, ca. 1985-2000 (Box-folder 118/6)
      Mostly includes photographs of Izzy Young and the Folklore Centrum. Includes several with daughter, Philomene Grandin.
    - Ulf Engstrom photographs, ca. 2005 (Box-folder 118/7)
      Photographic prints mostly by Ulf Engstrom of Izzy Young organizing a concert.
    - Folklore Center, Folklore Centrum, and folk musicians, ca. 1958-1992 (Box-folder 118/8)
      Includes photographic prints of Izzy Young and the Folklore Center and Folklore Centrum. Also includes photographs by David Gahr of Izzy Young with musicians and family members.
    - Family photographs, ca. 1940-1950 (Box-folder 119/1)
      Two unidentified photographs (one is likely with a young Izzy Young).
    - Folklore Center, Washington Square Park, Folklore Centrum, and Izzy Young portraits, ca. 1958-2013 (Box-folder 119/2)
      Includes negatives of Bob Dylan drawing, contact sheets from 1971, and photographic prints from the Folklore Center, Washington Square Park, and the Folklore Centrum. Includes portaits of Izzy Young.
    - Folklore Center and folk scene photographs, ca. 1958-1990 (Box-folder 119/3)
      Includes photograph by Ann Charters (with inscription on back) of Izzy Young with Sam Charters, Memphis Willie B., Furry Lewis, and Gus Canon. Photographs by David Gahr of the Folklore Center, Izzy Young, and folk musicians (including Phil Ochs and Pete Seeger). Also includes photographs of Izzy Young's brother and mother.
    - Music photographs, Sweden, ca. 1975-2005 (Box-folder 119/4)
      Includes photographs of musicians, artists, and friends and family.
    - Folklore Centrum and other Sweden photographs, ca. 1980-2014 (Box-folder 119/5)
    - Folklore Centrum and music photographs, Sweden, ca. 1980-2010 (Box-folder 119/6)
  - Subseries B: Color photographs
    - Negatives, ca. 1985-2005 (Box-folder 119/7)
      Includes images of Izzy Young and folk musicians.
    - Labelled photographic print from Folklore Center opening, 1957-04-06 (Box-folder 119/8)
      Photograph includes writing from Izzy Young identifying the musicians in the photograph, who include Jean Ritchie, Carolyn Hester, and Happy Traum.
    - Folklore Centrum and other Sweden photographs, ca. 1987-2010 (Box-folder 119/9-12)
      Includes photographs of Izzy Young and the Folklore Centrum, and other photographs of Young and friends in Sweden. Includes photographs of Young with Nathan Salsburg.
    - Experience Music Project event, Seattle, ca. 2000-2010 (Box-folder 119/13)
      Includes photographs of Izzy Young, John Cohen, and others at an event related to the Experience Music Project in Seattle, Washington. Also includes photographs taken around the city.
    - Folklore Centrum and other Sweden photographs, ca. 2003-2007 (Box-folder 120/1)
      Photographs that were removed from binder in box 101. Includes photographs of Izzy Young and the Folklore Centrum, and other photographs of Young and friends in Sweden. Also includes photographs of Young and John Cohen in a conference panel.
    - Folklore Centrum and other Sweden photographs, ca. 1978-2010 (Box-folder 120/2-3)
      Includes photographs of Izzy Young and the Folklore Centrum, and other photographs of Young and friends in Sweden. Includes photograph of Young with his mother. Also includes one photograph of Young in New York City at the former site of the Folklore Center.
  - Subseries C: Oversize photographs
    Black-and-white and color photographs are separated. Includes images of Izzy Young, folk musicians, and the Folklore Centrum.
    - Izzy Young at work, ca. 1985-2000 (Box-folder 121/1)
      Black-and-white photographic prints of Izzy Young working at the Folklore Centrum.
    - Izzy Young portraits, ca. 1985-2000 (Box-folder 121/2)
      Black-and-white photographs of Izzy Young at a square dance, as well as portraits.
    - Folklore Centrum and music photographs, ca. 1975-2014 (Box-folder 121/3)
      Black-and-white photographs of Izzy Young and the Folklore Centrum, Pete Seeger, and square dancing.
    - Folklore Centrum and music photographs, ca. 1990-2015 (Box-folder 121/4)
      Color photographs of Izzy Young and the Folklore Centrum. Includes photographs of Young with musician friends, including Patti Smith.
- Series IV: Optical media, ca. 1990-2010
  Optical media is unprocessed, and titles are derived from writing on containers and labels.
  - Andrea, Adreas, Caro, and Izzy live at the Folklore Centrum, October 24, 2013, 2013-10-24 (Item-id afc2015040_cf01)
  - To Hear Your Banjo Play, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf02)
    Audio from film about Pete Seeger.
  - DVD for Izzy Young from Francesca Terberg, UK, October 2010 (Item-id afc2015040_cf03)
  - Pete Seeger Interview, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf04)
    Part 1 and 2.
  - Izzy Young, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf05)
  - Izzy Young, 60 years, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf06)
  - Izzy Young diary, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf07)
    Disc 1 of 2, hi-res (TIFs); photos by Beth Mann (EMP).
  - Izzy Young diary, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf08)
    Disc 2 of 2, hi-res (TIFs); photos by Beth Mann (EMP).
  - Izzy Young diary, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf09)
    Disc 1 of 1, low-res (JPEGs); photos by Beth Mann (EMP).
  - Izzy=Dylan, The Bomb; "Talkin' Folklore," scan, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf10)
  - Izzy Young interview on music 101, May 28, 2011 (Item-id afc2015040_cf11)
  - Izzy foton ur Anna Linder's mobil… Izzy 80 ars kalas Izzy Korrloser, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf12)
  - Reportage our Izzy Young publ Folke 24/5, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf13)
  - Gazell, Izzy Young documentary, "Talking Folklore Center," undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf14)
  - Pete Seeger, part 1 of 2, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf15)
  - Pete Seeger, part I & II, "Pal time coded," undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf16)
  - [Pete] Seeger live Sweden, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf17)
  - Town Hall, NYC, April 12, 1963 (Item-id afc2015040_cf18)
    DNR, 1 of 2
  - Town Hall, NYC, April 12, 1963 (Item-id afc2015040_cf19)
    DNR, 2 of 2
  - Bob Dylan's American Journey, 1956-1966, November 19-20, 2004 (Item-id afc2015040_cf20)
  - Bob Dylan's American Journey, 1956-1966, November 19-20, 2004 (Item-id afc2015040_cf21)
  - EMP Panel: Bob Dylan: As We Remember Him, 2004 (Item-id afc2015040_cf22)
    Part 1 (EMP Seattle 2004)
  - CG-AT-022, CG-AT-023, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf23)
    From [Les] Blank Archives.
  - Heads Up 79: Irwin Silber memorial, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf24)
    Part 1 of 2 (BBSimmow Producer).
  - Heads Up 79: Irwin Silber memorial, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf25)
    Part 2 of 2 (BBSimmow Producer).
  - Oscar Brand shows, 1961, 1963 (Item-id afc2015040_cf26)
  - CG-AT-017-021 for Izzy (Cynthia Gooding), undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf27)
  - Townes Van Zandt Live at the Old Quarter, disc 1, undated (Item-id afc2015040_cf28)
    Likely a copy of the published 1973 album.
- Series V: Artifacts, ca. 1950-1990
  Includes artwork by artist and filmmaker, Harry Smith.
  - Harry Smith string art, ca. 1950-1990 (Box 122)
    Framed original piece.
  - Harry Smith prints, ca. 1950-1990 (Box 123)
    Original artwork on cardboard by Smith.
  - Diagram of Harry Smith trip, ca. 1950-1990 (Box 126)
- Series VI: Publications
  Listing of publications included in the Izzy Young collection.
  - Subseries A: Published materials
    Publications from Izzy Young's personal collection, and from the Folklore Center and Folklore Centrum's collections.
    - Ballads of Sacco & Vanzetti. Commissioned by Moses Asch - 1945. Composed and sung by Woody Guthrie - 1946-47., 1960 (Box-folder 124/1)
      Edited by Moses Asch and Irwin Silber.
    - From a Swedish notebook, 1972 (Box-folder 124/2)
      Samuel Charters. Inscribed message to Izzy Young by Charters.
    - Square dancing: a history, 1957 (Box-folder 124/3)
      S. Foster Damon. Includes Izzy Young's handwritten notes.
    - Analytical survey of Anglo-American traditional erotica, 1973 (Box-folder 124/4)
      Frank Hoffman. Inscribed message from author to Izzy Young.
    - Partners all - Places all!, 1949 (Box-folder 124/5)
      Miriam H. Kirkell and Irma K. Schaffnit. Includes handwritten notes and stamp from Folklore Centrum and People's Songs, Inc.
    - Out of the blues, 2013 (Box-folder 124/6)
      Brian D. Kramer
    - The nearly complete collection of Woody Guthrie songs. A collection of songs by America's foremost balladeer. 1963 (Box-folder 124/7)
      Compiled and edited by Pete Seeger. New York, N.Y.: Ludlow Music, Inc., 1963. Includes inscription by Izzy Young from 2013.
    - The Morris book: with a description of dances as performed by the Morrismen of England. Part II., 1919 (Box-folder 124/8)
      Cecil Sharp and Herbert C. Macilwaine. (parts 1-3 in general collection)
    - The Notebooks of Margot Mayo. Book I., 1934-1937 (Box-folder 125/1)
      Finding aid for Margot Mayo collection. American Square Dance Group.
  - Subseries B: Pamphlets and serials
    - 12 home made square dances, 1948 (Box-folder 125/2)
      Charley Thomas.
    - Sisters in song: a collection of new songs from the women's liberation movement, ca. 1977 (Box-folder 125/3)
    - The Midwest dancer: a magazine of round and square dancing. Vol 8, no. 5., 1959-04 (Box-folder 125/4)
    - New York Supreme Court, 1961 (Box-folder 125/5)
      Petitioner Israel G. Young against Newbold Morris, Commissioner of Parks of the City of New York.
    - "Some Cuna Indian animal stories, with original texts" (from Ethnological Studies, 4, 1937)., 1937 (Box-folder 125/6)
      Henry Wassen.
    - Dizzy dances. Volume II., 1986 (Box-folder 125/7)
      Gene Hubert.
    - Square dance: Formerly American squares. Vol 22, no. 4., 1966-12 (Box-folder 125/8)
      Jerry Haag.
    - Square dance 2, 1983 (Box-folder 125/9)
      Inger Toreld.